Last year ...
لقد كان العام الماضي ...
was hell.
جحيماً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was my first time eating Nigerian "jollof."
كانت المرة الأولى التي أتناولُ فيها "أرز الجولوف" النيجيري.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, in all seriousness,
في الواقع، بكل جدية،
I was going through a lot of personal turmoil.
كنت أمرّ بالكثير من الاضطرابات الشخصية.
Faced with enormous stress,
واجهتُ توترًا هائلًا،
I suffered an anxiety attack.
وعانيت من نوبة قلق.
On some days, I could do no work.
في بعض الأيام، لم يكن باستطاعتي العمل.
On other days,
وفي بعضها الآخر،
I just wanted to lay in my bed and cry.
أردتُ فقط أن أرقد على سريري وأبكي.
My doctor asked if I'd like to speak with a mental health professional
سألني طبيبي إن كنتُ أرغبُ في التحدث إلى مختص الصحة العقلية
about my stress and anxiety.
عن توتري وقلقي.
Mental health?
صحة عقلية؟
I clammed up and violently shook my head in protest.
رفضتُ الحديث والرد، وهززت رأسي محتجاً بشدة.
I felt a profound sense of a shame.
شعرت بخزيٍ عميق.
I felt the weight of stigma.
شعرت بتأثير وصمة العار،
I have a loving, supportive family
لدي عائلة محبة وداعمة،
and incredibly loyal friends,
وأصدقاء مخلصون على نحو لا يصدق،
yet I could not entertain the idea of speaking to anyone
رغم ذلك لم أستسغ فكرة التحدث مع أي أحد
about my feeling of pain.
عن شعوري بالألم.
I felt suffocated by the rigid architecture
شعرت بالاختناق اتجاه الصورة النمطية المتزمتة القاسية
of our African masculinity.
لذكورتنا الإفريقية.
"People have real problems, Sangu.
"سانغو، لدى الناس مشاكل حقيقية،
Get over yourself!"
تمالك نفسك!"
The first time I heard "mental health,"
كانت أول مرة أسمع فيها "صحة عقلية،"
I was a boarding school student fresh off the boat from Ghana,
عندما كنت طالباً في مدرسة داخلية، مهاجرًا جديدًا قادمًا من غانا.
at the Peddie School in New Jersey.
في (مدرسة بيديي) في ولاية ( نيو جيرسي).
I had just gone through the brutal experience
كنت أمرٌ حينها بتجربة مريعة
of losing seven loved ones in the same month.
نتيجة فقدان 7 أحباء في نفس الشهر.
The school nurse,
فممرضة المدرسة
concerned about what I'd gone through -- God bless her soul --
شعرتْ بالقلق حول ما أمرّ به -- فليباركها الله --
she inquired about my mental health.
استفسرت عن حال صحتي العقلية.
"Is she mental?" I thought.
تساءلتُ، "هل هي مجنونة؟"
Does she not know I'm an African man?
ألا تعرف أنني رجل إفريقي؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Like Okonkwo in "Things Fall Apart,"
مثل (أوكونكو) في رواية "الأشياء تتداعى،"
we African men neither process nor express our emotions.
نحن الرجال الأفارقة لا نعالج ولا نعبّر عن مشاعرنا.
We deal with our problems.
بل نتعامل مع مشاكلنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I called my brother and laughed about "Oyibo" people -- white people --
هاتفتُ أخي وسخرنا حول "الأوييبو/ العالم الغربي"-- الأشخاص البيض --
and their strange diseases --
وأمراضهم الغريبة --
depression, ADD and those "weird things."
الاكتئاب واضطراب نقص الانتباه (ADD) وتلك "الأشياء الغريبة."
Growing up in West Africa,
نتيجة ترعري في غرب إفريقيا،
when people used the term "mental," what came to mind was a madman
عندما يستخدم الناس مصطلح "عقلي،" ما يتبادر إلى الذهن هو رجل مجنون
with dirty, dread-locked hair,
دو شعر مُجدّل متسخ،
bumbling around half-naked on the streets.
يتسكعُ في الطرقات نصف عاري وبلا هدىً.
We all know this man.
يعرفُ جميعنا هذا الرجل.
Our parents warned us about him.
حذرنا آباؤنا منه.
"Mommy, mommy, why is he mad?"
"أمي، أمي، لماذا هو مجنون؟"
"Drugs!
"العقاقير!
If you even look at drugs, you end up like him."
إن نظرت حتى إلى العقاقير، سينتهي بك الأمر مثله."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Come down with pneumonia,
إذا أصيب أحدكم بإلتهاب رئوي،
and your mother will rush you to the nearest hospital
وستهرع بك والدتك لأقرب مستشفى
for medical treatment.
لتلقي العلاج الطبي.
But dare to declare depression,
لكن تجرّأ وصرّح بالاكتئاب،
and your local pastor will be driving out demons
وسيتولى القس المحلي في قريتك أمر إخراج الأرواح الشريرة
and blaming witches in your village.
وسيُلقي اللوم على ساحرات القرية.
According to the World Health Organization,
حسب منظمة الصحة العالمية،
mental health is about being able to cope
الصحة العقلية هي القدرة على مواجهة
with the normal stressors of life;
الضغطوطات والتوترات الطبيعية للحياة؛
to work productively and fruitfully;
وأن تمارس العمل بشكل مُنتج ومثمر
and to be able to make a contribution to your community.
وأن تكون قادراً على المساهمة في مجتمعك.
Mental health includes our emotional, psychological and social well-being.
تشمل الصحة العقلية الراحة والرفاهية العاطفية والنفسية والاجتماعية.
Globally, 75 percent of all mental illness cases
عالمياً، 75% من مجمل حالات الأمراض العقلية
can be found in low-income countries.
يمكنُ أن توجد في الدول ذات الدخل المحدود.
Yet most African governments
رغم ذلك، أغلب الحكومات الإفريقية
invest less than one percent of their health care budget
تستثمر أقل من 1% من ميزانيتها للرعاية الصحية
in mental health.
لصالح الصحة العقلية.
Even worse,
بل أسوء من ذلك،
we have a severe shortage of psychiatrists in Africa.
نعاني من نقص حاد في عدد الأطباء النفسيين في إفريقيا.
Nigeria, for example, is estimated to have 200 --
لدى نيجيريا، على سبيل المثال، ما يُقدّرُ بـِ 200 طبيب نفسي
in a country of almost 200 million.
في بلد تعداد سكانه 200 مليون نسمة.
In all of Africa,
في عموم إفريقيا،
90 percent of our people lack access to treatment.
لا يستطيع 90% من أهلنا الحصول على العناية.
As a result,
نتيجة لذلك،
we suffer in solitude,
نعاني في عزلة،
silenced by stigma.
مجبرين على الصمت بسبب وصمة العار.
We as Africans often respond to mental health with distance,
غالباً ما نستجيب نحن الأفارقة للصحة العقلية بالابتعاد،
ignorance,
والتجاهل،
guilt,
والشعور بالذنب،
fear
والخوف،
and anger.
والغضب.
In a study conducted by Arboleda-Flórez,
في دراسة أجراها الدكتور: (خوليو أربوليدا فلوريز)
directly asking, "What is the cause of mental illness?"
سأل سؤالاً مباشراً، "ما هو سبب المرض العقلي؟"
34 percent of Nigerian respondents cited drug misuse;
استشهد 34% من المستطلعين النيجيريين بسوء استخدام المخدرات؛
19 percent said divine wrath and the will of God --
وقال 19% أنه بسبب الغضب الإلهي وإرادة الله --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
12 percent,
وقال 12%
witchcraft and spiritual possession.
أنها بسبب الشعوذة والسحر والمس الشيطاني.
But few cited other known causes of mental illness,
واستشهد عدد قليل بأسباب أخرى معروفة للمرض العقلي،
like genetics,
مثل العوامل الوراثية/ الجينات،
socioeconomic status,
الحالة الاجتماعية الاقتصادية،
war,
والحرب،
conflict
والنزاع،
or the loss of a loved one.
أو فقدان شخص عزيز.
The stigmatization against mental illness
الوصم بالمرض العقلي
often results in the ostracizing and demonizing of sufferers.
يؤدي غالبًا إلى نبذ وشيطنة المصابين.
Photojournalist Robin Hammond has documented some of these abuses ...
وثّق المصور الصحفي (روبن هاموند) بعض هذه الانتهاكات ...
in Uganda,
في أوغندا،
in Somalia,
وفي الصومال،
and here in Nigeria.
وهنا في نيجيريا.
For me,
بالنسبة لي،
the stigma is personal.
وصمة العار هي شيءٌ شخصي.
In 2009,
في العام 2009،
I received a frantic call in the middle of the night.
تلقيت مكالمة شديدة الاهتياج في منتصف الليل.
My best friend in the world --
أعز أصدقائي في الدنيا --
a brilliant, philosophical, charming, hip young man --
شاب ذكي رابط الجأش جذاب مجارٍ للموضة --
was diagnosed with schizophrenia.
تم تشخيص حالته بالفُصام.
I witnessed some of the friends we'd grown up with recoil.
شاهدت بعض أصدقاء الطفولة ممن يتسمون بالتردد والحيرة.
I heard the snickers.
سمعتٌ القهقهات.
I heard the whispers.
سمعت الهمسات.
"Did you hear he has gone mad?"
"هل سمعت أنه أصيب بالجنون؟"
(Kru English) "He has gone crazy!"
"لقد أصيب بالجنون!"
Derogatory, demeaning commentary about his condition --
الازدراء والتعليق المهين على حالته --
words we would never say about someone with cancer
كلمات سوف لن نصف بها شخصاً مصاباً بالسرطان
or someone with malaria.
أو الملاريا.
Somehow, when it comes to mental illness,
بطريقة ما، حينما يتعلق الأمر بالصحة العقلية،
our ignorance eviscerates all empathy.
ينتزعُ جهلنا كل التعاطف.
I stood by his side as his community isolated him,
وقفتُ إلى جانبه بينما عزله مجتمعه،
but our love never wavered.
لكن لم يضطرب حبنا لبعضنا البعض أبداً.
Tacitly, I became passionate about mental health.
ضمنياً، أصبحت شغوفاً بالصحة العقلية.
Inspired by his plight,
مستمداً الإلهام من محنته،
I helped found the mental health special interest alumni group
ساعدت في إنشاء مجموعة خريجي المهتمين بالصحة النفسية
at my college.
في كليتي.
And during my tenure as a resident tutor in graduate school,
وخلال فترة تولي منصبي كمدرس مقيم في مدرسة الدراسات العليا،
I supported many undergraduates with their mental health challenges.
دعمتُ العديد من الطلاب الجامعيين ممن كانوا يعانون من تحديات الصحة العقلية.
I saw African students struggle
رأيت طلاباً أفارقة يصارعون
and unable to speak to anyone.
ولا يستطيعون التحدث مع أي أحد.
Even with this knowledge and with their stories in tow,
وعلى الرغم من هذه المعرفة وبصحبة قصصهم،
I, in turn, struggled,
أنا، بدوري، صارعت أيضاً،
and could not speak to anyone when I faced my own anxiety,
ولم أستطع التحدّث مع أي كان حين انتابني القلق،
so deep is our fear of being the madman.
منغمسين جدًا في خوفنا من أن نصبح الرجل المجنون.
All of us --
جميعنا --
but we Africans especially --
ولكن نحنُ الأفارقة على وجه الخصوص --
need to realize that our mental struggles do not detract from our virility,
بحاجة أن ندرك أن صراعاتنا العقلية لا تنتقص من رجولتنا،
nor does our trauma taint our strength.
ولا تلطخُ الصدمة قوتنا.
We need to see mental health as important as physical health.
نحتاج أن نرى الصحة العقلية مهمة كما هي الصحة الجسدية.
We need to stop suffering in silence.
نحتاج أن نتوقف عن المعاناة في صمت.
We must stop stigmatizing disease
لا بد أن نتوقف عن وصم المرض
and traumatizing the afflicted.
والحاق الأذى بالمتضررين.
Talk to your friends.
تحدّث إلى أصدقائك.
Talk to your loved ones.
تحدث إلى أحبائك.
Talk to health professionals.
تحدث إلى مختصي الصحة.
Be vulnerable.
كنُ ضعيفًا واهنًا.
Do so with the confidence
افعل ذلك بثقة
that you are not alone.
أنك لست وحيداً.
Speak up if you're struggling.
اجهر بالقول إن كنت تصارع.
Being honest about how we feel
أن نكون صادقين حول ماهية مشاعرنا
does not make us weak;
لا يجعلنا ضعفاء؛
it makes us human.
بل يجعلنا بشراً.
It is time to end the stigma associated with mental illness.
حان الوقت لإنهاء الوصمة المرتبطة بالمرض العقلي.
So the next time your hear "mental,"
لذا في المرة القادمة حينما تسمع كلمة "عقلي،"
do not just think of the madman.
لا تفكر فقط في الرجل المجنون.
Think of me.
بل فكر فيّ أنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.